Guide to the Nicholas Low Papers Supplement 1784-1829 MS 392.1
New-York Historical Society
Nicholas Low Papers Supplement
1784-1829
New-York Historical Society
MS 392.1
0.5 Linear feet
no content
Provenance
Donation by Peter McBean, 1989
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1739 Mar. 30 Nicholas Low born near New Brunswick, NJ to Cornelius Low, Jr. and Johanna (Gouverneur) Low
1785 Low, already established as a prominent New York City businessman, is elected a director of the Bank of New York. Soon thereafter, he becomes a director of the NY branch of the Bank of the United States.
1788 Low, a member of the Assembly, is a Federalist member of the state constitutional convention in Poughkeepsie.
1790-1823 Low manages the finances of Rufus King, a fellow Federalist and government official.
[1800-1826] Low's chief interest is in the role of proprietor and land speculator in New York City and State.
1826 Nov. 15 Low dies in New York City
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of 167 items, the majority of which is correspondence, chiefly letters sent to Low by the statesman Rufus King concerning financial matters and, to some extent, political affairs. The remainder of the collection is made up of correspondence received by Low from other correspondents. There is one letter penned by Low himself as well as a portion of Nicholas Low's father Cornelius Low's will.
Rufus King's early letters to Low, which span the years 1790 to 1792, discuss matters of political affairs including: the establishment of a national bank; the Bank of North America and the Bank of New York; and the gubernatorial election in New York. Rufus King served as minister to Great Britain from 1796 to 1803. During this time, King's letters to Low discuss both domestic and international politics as well as his personal finances. As the years progress, the later correspondence from King primarily deals with his personal finances.
Arrangement
Chronological arrangement within each series.
This collection is organized into nine series.
Legal documents.; Business papers; United States -- Commerce.; New York (N.Y.) -- Commerce.; Correspondence.; Banks and banking -- United States.; National banks (United States); Seizure of vessels and cargoes; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815; Finance, Personal; France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799.; Great Britain -- History -- 1789-1820.; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1789-1809.; Bank of New York; Bank of North America; Benson, Egbert, 1746-1833; King, Rufus, 1755-1827; Knox, Henry, 1750-1806; Madison, James, 1751-1836
- Series I: Rufus King, Letters sent to Nicholas Low, 1790-1823
  Scope and Contents note
  The letters between 1790 and 1823 span King's career as a U.S. Senator, from his first term to his last, and his time spent as Minister to Great Britain. The sustained topic of these letters is the state of King's financial affairs. The letters cast a great deal of light on the investments and financial interests of King and to the manner in which Low controlled them. Along with King's personal finances, the letters often turn to the domestic and international issues of the day. During King's first term as senator, he was especially concerned with the issue of banking in the United States. The early letters in this series include his thoughts on the establishment of the Bank of the United States and the role of the Bank of North America and the Bank of New York. Other topics include the defeat of Arthur St. Clair's army by the Indians, the 1792 campaign for governor in New York, William Duer's financial problems and a plan by Genet to send 2,000 men down the Mississippi River to take New Orleans and Florida.
  After assuming the position of Minister to Great Britain in 1796, King's letters move away from the domestic concerns of the United States and are dominated by the war between England and France. From 1796 to 1803, King describes the course of the war, periodic negotiations for peace, developments and shifts in alliances (especially the role of North European powers) and popular opinion towards the war. As a representative from the United States, King's main concerns were the seizure of American ships by England and France, the effects of the war on American trade and the intentions of European powers in North America during and after the war. Of special interest is the letter dated October 10, 1798, which links Thomas Paine with advice given to the French on how to pursue a war against the United States. Along with reports on the war, King discusses trade prospects in Europe, describes domestic affairs in England and Ireland and makes general observations on the political scene in the United States. When King returned to the United States and returned to the Senate, his letters to Low tended to focus much more on his financial affairs and less on the work he was involved with and the issues of the nation.
  - Establishment of a national bank; resolution on system for funding the public debt, 1790 Dec. 13 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Surprise attack by Indians on St. Clair's army; information on the Bank of the United States, 1791 Dec. 8 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Union of national and state banks; purchase of 30 or 40 scripts from (?) bank, 1791 Dec. 11 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Indians attack on St. Clair's army, 1791 Dec. 11 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Competition between state and national banks, 1791 Dec. 18 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Bank of New York, 1792 Jan. 22 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Bank of North America and bank notes, 1792 Jan. 29 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Bank and branches in New York and Boston; Jay's election campaign for Governor of New York, 1792 Mar. 1 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Bank branch in New York; election of governor; Duer's failure to make payment at the Bank of New York, 1792 Mar. 11 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Financial problems for the Bank of New York, 1792 Mar. 14 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Duer and his friends; Purchase of New York Bank stock, 1792 Mar. 19 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Bank of North America; Bank of the United States; Bank of New York; Competition between the three, 1792 Mar. 21 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Banks, Manufacturing Society, 1792 Mar. 26 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Bank, 1792 Apr. 1 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Bank and the "complete assumption" of debt, 1792 Apr. 1 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Bank stocks; banks in general, 1792 Apr. 8 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Personal finances, 1792 Apr. 8 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Bank of the United States; Nomination of Wayne to command army in place of St. Clair, 1792 Apr. 9 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Bank; election of Governor of New York; bank stocks, 1792 Apr. 29 (Box 1, Folder 1790-1792)
  - Petition against Madison's resolution; a ship report from Bordeaux; French West Indies, 1794 Feb. 16 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Prospects of peace/war with England; Low putting together a petition to Congress; 2,000 men under Clark and Logan, commissioned by Genet, plan to descend the Mississippi River and take New Orleans and Florida (Spain was notified of these intentions)., 1794 Mar. 2 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - A resolution put together in New York; the question of war with England, 1794 Mar. 9 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Personal finances, 1795 Dec. 14 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Personal finances, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Personal finances, 1796 Jan. 24 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Establishment of Mutual Insurance Company, 1796 Jan. 29 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Wine shipment, 1796 Feb. 27 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Effects of affairs with England on the insurance of ships, 1796 Apr. 17 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Obtaining passage to London, 1796 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Personal finances, 1796 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Personal finances, 1796 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Personal finances, 1796 Aug. 1 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Personal finances, 1796 Sept. 9 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Letter of introduction for Mr. MacDonald and Mr. Rush, 1796 Dec. 6 (Box 1, Folder 1794-1796)
  - Bank of England has stopped using spice and is continuing with the experiment with paper money; England's relations with France, 1797 Mar. 11 (Box 1, Folder 1797)
  - Insurance of shipping vessels; the receptiveness of French leaders to peace; the call for peace in England, 1797 Apr. 26 (Box 1, Folder 1797)
  - Personal finances; observations on current tensions in England (Ireland; Occupation on Thames River); conflict with England and France, 1797 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 1797)
  - Letter of introduction for General Korusko(?), 1797 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 1797)
  - Concern that his letters have been seized; opinions on the war; seizure of ships during the war; paper currency in England; stocks, 1797 Aug. 16 (Box 1, Folder 1797)
  - Personal finances; congratulations on the birth of Low's second son, 1797 Sept. 9 (Box 1, Folder 1797)
  - War between England and France; "The Army of England", 1797 Nov. 13 (Box 1, Folder 1797)
  - Low's need to secure King's financial security; comments on captured ships, 1798 Jan. 4 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - Defense of property in regards to American ships sailing in European waters and the possibility of sailing with convoys, 1798 Jan. 15 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - War with France and the effects on merchants in the United States, 1798 Feb. 7 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - Collection of personal debt; rebellion in Ireland, 1798 Apr. 6 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - Personal finances, 1798 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - Possible purchase of farm in Dutchess County, New York, 1798 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - An act of Parliament concerning additional foreign duties upon trade and navigation, 1798 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - Desire to purchase a farm in New York, 1798 Aug. 14 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - Personal finances, 1798 Sept. 25 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - The naval battle led by Admiral Nelson and the observation that the British are "now entire masters of the Mediterranean" and how that relates to the fate of Napoleon; France and Austria in conflict; Turks and Russians against the French; Thomas Paine's advice on how to pursue an attack against the United States; rebellion in Ireland, 1798 Oct. 10 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - Request for goods from home, 1798 Oct. 12 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - The French seizure of American vessels; trade prospects in Constantinople; war related taxes and public opinion in England, 1798 Nov. 9 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - Personal finances, 1798 Dec. 18 (Box 1, Folder 1798)
  - Personal affairs re: the house in New York City, 1799 Jan. 3 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - Neutral ships being seized by British and French, 1799 Jan. 24 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - Personal finances, 1799 Jan. 24 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - Personal finances, 1799 Feb. 26 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - Political affairs in Europe; commerce prospects, 1799 Feb. 26 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - An epidemic in New York City; the war between France and England, 1799 Apr. 19 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - Personal finances; Low's trip to India, 1799 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - Personal finances; the war, 1799 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - Low's and King's merchant trade; maritime system in England; personal finances; ship seizures in England, 1799 Sept. 26 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - Personal finances, 1799 Oct. 25 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - Personal finances; trade situation in Europe, 1799 Nov. 1 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - Setting up B. Dandridge up as a merchant in New York, 1799 Dec. 20 (Box 1, Folder 1799)
  - England, Austria and Russia and their commitment to war against France, 1800 Jan. 24 (Box 1, Folder 1800)
  - Letter of introduction for Mr. Dandridge, 1800 Feb. 21 (Box 1, Folder 1800)
  - Personal finances, 1800 Feb. 26 (Box 1, Folder 1800)
  - Supply of food in England; American trade in Europe and European colonies when peace comes, 1800 Mar. 8 (Box 1, Folder 1800)
  - The state of the war, 1800 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 1800)
  - Changes in political direction of the U.S. and the effect it will have on property, 1800 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1800)
  - Personal finances, 1800 Aug. 14 (Box 1, Folder 1800)
  - Life in England; possibilities of peace between Austria and France; American vessels traveling with convoys, 1800 Aug. 16 (Box 1, Folder 1800)
  - The politics of war, 1800 Sept. 2 (Box 1, Folder 1800)
  - Peace prospects; convoys, 1800 Sept. 11 (Box 1, Folder 1800)
  - Purchasing a farm in New York, 1800 Sept. 24 (Box 1, Folder 1800)
  - French convention and the prospect of peace, 1801 Mar. 4 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Personal finances; the war, 1801 Mar. 7 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Personal finances, 1801 Mar. 7 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - The war and prospects of peace; selling his house, 1801 Mar. 16 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Selling his house; the war and prospects of peace, 1801 Mar. 23 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - The war and prospects of peace, 1801 Apr. 11 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - The war and prospects of peace; the Northern League (The League of Northern Powers); the death of the Russian Emperor, 1801 Apr. 15 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Personal finances, 1801 Apr. 25 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Relations between England and the United States, 1801 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Bringing a case concerning ship seizures, 1801 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Sale of his house, 1801 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - The war; the Portugal Convention (?), 1801 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Personal finances, 1801 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Personal finances and house on Maiden Lane, 1801 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Personal finances, 1801 Aug. 14 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - England joyous over peace; the end of the blockade on U.S. naval vessels; general reaction to peace, 1801 Oct. 14 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - French military expedition to the West Indies, and, possibly, Louisiana and its effects on American trade; peace, 1801 Oct. 26 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Peace; French expedition to St. Domingo; the expedition's need for supplies, 1801 Dec. 26 (Box 1, Folder 1801)
  - Selling of Broadway house; personal finances, 1802 Mar. 15 (Box 1, Folder 1802)
  - Observations; St. Domingo expedition, 1802 Apr. 7 (Box 1, Folder 1802)
  - Selling his house to John J. Astor; personal finances; observations on British political scene, 1802 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 1802)
  - Selling his house to John J. Astor; personal finances; observations on British political scene, 1802 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 1802)
  - Personal finances, 1802 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 1802)
  - Sale of house to Astor; personal finances, 1802 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 1802)
  - Letter of introduction from Captain Upton of British Navy, 1802 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 1802)
  - Returning to the states; visiting Paris; political climate of Europe; prospects of continued peace, 1802 Dec. 3 (Box 1, Folder 1802)
  - Personal finances, 1803 Feb. 6 (Box 1, Folder 1803)
  - Deed to house, 1803 Feb. 10 (Box 1, Folder 1803)
  - Personal finances, 1803 Mar. 5 (Box 1, Folder 1803)
  - Relations between England and France and the possibility of war recommencing and how that will effect the French expedition of Louisiana, 1803 Mar. 9 (Box 1, Folder 1803)
  - Personal finances, 1805 Sept. 30 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Letter of introduction, 1807 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Personal finances, 1815 Mar. 22 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Personal finances (the cotton factory), 1815 Apr. 6 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Stock transfer to Low (official document), 1816 Nov. 9 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Congress' repeal of internal taxes, 1817 Dec. 13 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Personal finances; Congress, 1818 Jan. 9 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Personal finances, 1818 Jan. 16 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Personal finances, 1818 Jan. 17 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Personal finances, 1818 Jan. 21 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Personal finances, 1818 Jan. 23 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Death of (presumably) Low's wife, 1818 Apr. 16 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Personal finances; Bank of New York, 1823 Apr. 11 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Personal finances, 1823 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
  - Personal finances, 1823 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 1805-1823)
- Series II: Rufus King, Letter sent to Jonathan Burral, 1815
  General note
  Letter sent to Burral regarding Ballston Spa Company
  - Personal finances, Ballston Spa Company, 1815 Nov. 14 (Box 1, Folder 1815)
- Series III: Rufus King, Letters sent to Augustus Flemming, 1818-1824
  Letters sent to Flemming, who was most likely an assistant to Low, from King who was serving as a U.S. Senator from New York. All of the correspondence pertains to King's personal finances.
  - Personal finances, 1818 Aug. 14 (Box 1, Folder 1818-1824)
  - Personal finances, 1821 Aug. 8 (Box 1, Folder 1818-1824)
  - Personal finances, 1821 Nov. 27 (Box 1, Folder 1818-1824)
  - Personal finances, 1822 Dec. 3 (Box 1, Folder 1818-1824)
  - Personal finances, 1823 Aug. 2 (Box 1, Folder 1818-1824)
  - Personal finances, 1823 Oct. 17 (Box 1, Folder 1818-1824)
  - Personal finances, 1823 Oct. 31 (Box 1, Folder 1818-1824)
  - Personal finances, 1823 Nov. 10 (Box 1, Folder 1818-1824)
  - Personal finances, 1824 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 1818-1824)
- Series IV: Rufus King, Power of Attorney, 1802
  King gives power of attorney to Low.
  - Power of attorney from King to Low, 1802 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 1802)
- Series V: Nicholas Low, letters received (excluding King letters), 1784-1829
  Letters sent to Low by prominent local, state, and national figures including Egbert Benson, Robert Morris, Samuel Smith, General Henry Knox and James Madison. The letters chiefly concern Low's mercantile and financial activities. Of special note is a letter which gives a detailed description of the sinking of the ship Bengal, presumably owned by Low.
  - Smith Sam L. Thank you letter for sweet meats sent to Knewels, 1784 Aug. 3 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Livingston, Peter R. Unable to take up a draft of $300, 1785 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Egbert, Benson. Business transactions, 1790 Feb. 4 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Egbert, Benson. Business transactions, 1791 Feb. 4 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Buckholm, Thomas. Bill of landing, a case containing "a marble statue of the late eminent Dr. Franklyn", 1791 Oct. 10 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Morris, Robert. Received the wrong wine, 1793 Apr. 29 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Noailles, Nisc. Wants a letter directed to R. Morris' home, 1793 Sept. 6 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Watts, John. Financial dealings; information on debate regarding W. Clarke's proposition to prohibit commerce with England and Ireland, 1794 Apr. 10 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Bingham, William. Concerning a wine shipment, 1797 Jan. 12 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Cutting, John B. Letter of introduction for Lord Henry Stuart, 1798 Apr. 3 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Morris, Thomas. Regarding a deed, 1799 Apr. 7 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Madison, James. R. King's passage back to the United States., 1802 Oct. 9 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Knox, Henry, General. Information on Patterson Manufactory instituted under the auspices of "your lamentable friend Hamilton", 1805 Dec. 16 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - DeRoven, Henry. Insurance of money aboard the Bengal bound for Buenos Aires, 1806 Dec. 5 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - DeRoven, Henry. Sinking of (Low's?) ship Bengal, 1807 Apr. 4 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Mumford, Gordon. Letter to the President of the United States, 1808 Mar. 12 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Conant, George C. Financial matters, 1809 July 24 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Gay, A. Erection of a New York bath house on Beaver Street, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Ogden, Gouverneur. Financial matters, 1821 Sept. 18 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Ogden, David B. Low living with his daughter, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
  - Weddington, J. Public auction of pew in Trinity Church, 1829 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 1784-1829)
- Series VI: Nicholas Low, Miscellaneous Documents, 1801-1828
  A collection of documents relating to Low. Included within this series are a bill of sale for the ship, Lace; a request issued by the American Consulate, Amsterdam, for safe passage for the ship, Eugenia; a copy of an act by the New York State Legislature; legal opinions given on the seizure of a ship by the British and other documents; a financial contract; a circular regarding the Park Theatre.
  - Bill of sale for vessel Lace, 1801 Mar. 4 (Box 1, Folder 1801-1828)
  - Request for safe passage of vessel Eugenia by American consulate, Amsterdam, 1801 Oct. 16 (Box 1, Folder 1801-1828)
  - Contract, 1818 Oct. 26 (Box 1, Folder 1801-1828)
  - A copy of an act of the New York State Legislature, [1823 Feb. 28] (Box 1, Folder 1801-1828)
  - Circular re: Park Theatre, 1828 Apr. 14 (Box 1, Folder 1801-1828)
- Series VII: Cornelius Low, Last Will, [1784], undated
  The will of Nicholas Low's father, Cornelius
  - The will of Cornelius Low, Nicholas Low's father, undated [proved June 30, 1784] (Box 1, Folder Cornelius Low's last will)
- Series VIII: Nicholas Low, Letter sent, undated
  Fragment of a draft of a letter concerning the motives behind the people who fled from Philadelphia and sought shelter in New York City.
  - Letter sent by Nicholas Low, fragment of draft, undated (Box 1, Folder Nicholas Low, Letter sent)
- Series IX: Gouverneur Ogden, Letter sent to Augustus Flemming, 1829
  Letter sent to Augustus Flemming by Gouverneur Ogden re: personal finances
  - Ogden letter to Flemming, 1829 Feb. 24 (Box 1, Folder 1829)